Naomi Muggleton

naomi.muggleton@gmail.com • +44(0) 77 8698 7817 • github.com/nmuggleton • Google Scholar

Department of Social Policy and Intervention • University of Oxford • Oxford • United Kingdom

Summary

I am a postdoctoral researcher who discovers natural experiments in digital footprints to understand human behaviour.

My specialism is behavioural science and I have training in psychology, econometrics, and machine learning. I currently work on an ERC-funded project at the University of Oxford to understand the formation, maintenance, and perception of elite groups in society.

I use large, observational datasets (e.g., mass-transactional that promote gender equality in 60 countries.

data, web-scraped records, location geo-tags) to identify social trends in health, well-being, and inequality.

I've also worked on industry-funded projects at the Alan Turing Institute, Lloyds Banking Group, Schroders Personal Wealth, The British Museum, and Player LENS. My doctoral research examined the evolutionary drivers of inequality. In particular, I examined ecological and economic triggers that promote gender equality in 60 countries.

Education

PhD Psychology	Coventry, UK
University of Warwick	2015–2019
MSc Behavioural and Economic Science	Coventry, UK
University of Warwick	2013–2014
BSc Psychology	Coventry, UK
University of Warwick	2010–2013

Research and Industry Experience

Department of Social Policy and Intervention, University of Oxford	Oxford, UK
Postdoctoral Fellow in Computational Social Science	October 2020 – September 2022
Funded by the European Research Council	
Behavioural Science Group, Warwick Business School	Coventry, UK
Postdoctoral Research Fellow in Behavioural Science	October 2018 – September 2020
Funded by Lloyds Banking Group	
The Alan Turing Institute	British Library, UK
Droingt I and	December 2019

Project Lead
Funded by Player LENS

The Alan Turing Institute

Visiting Behavioural Scientist

Funded by The British Museum

December 2018

British Library, UK June – September 2018

Publications

Working Papers

(Most developed papers at the top)

Muggleton, N., Parpart, P., Newall, P., Leake, D., Gathergood, J., & Stewart, N. Gambling-related harm in mass transaction data. *Third submission invited, Nature Human Behaviour.*

Muggleton, N. & Fincher, C. Opportunity, economic inequality, and ecology: Individual and ecological differences interact to produce world-wide variation in gender values. *Out for review, Political Psychology.*

Muggleton, N., Quispe-Torreblanca, E., Leake, D., Gathergood, J., & Stewart, N. Spending entropy and future financial distress. *Working paper.* doi: 10.31234/osf.io/qabgm.

Muggleton, N., Trendl, A., Walasek, L., Leake, D., Gathergood, J., & Stewart, N. Inequality at work and status-signalling luxury consumption. *Working paper*.

Published

Muggleton, N. K., Tarran, S., & Fincher, C. L. (2019). Who punishes promiscuous women? Both women and men are prejudiced towards sexually-accessible women, but only women inflict costly punishment. *Evolution and Human Behavior*, 40(3), 259–268. doi: 10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2018.12.003.

Muggleton, N. K., & Fincher, C. L. (2018). You're not my type: Do conservatives have a bias for seeing long-term mates? *Evolution and Human Behavior*, 39(6), 652–663. doi: 10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2018.06.009.

Muggleton, N. K., & Fincher, C. L. (2017). Unrestricted sexuality promotes distinctive short- and long-term mate preferences in women. *Personality and Individual Differences*, 111, 169–174. doi: 10.1016/j.paid.2017.01.054

Muggleton, N. K., & Fincher, C. L. (2016). The effects of disease vulnerability on preferences for self-similar scent. *Evolutionary Psychological Science*, 2(2), 129–139. doi: 10.1007/s40806-016-0043-y

Awards, Fellowships, and Grants

2018

PhD student publication of the year, University of Warwick (£100)

Research-funded grant, The Alan Turing Institute and The British Museum (£7,500)

European Human Behaviour and Evolution Association's (EHBEA) Student Research Grant (€500)

2017

Experimental Psychological Society's (EPS) Grindley Grant (£500)

2016

EHBEA Student Research Grant (€500)

2015

University of Warwick PhD Fellowship in Psychology (£60,000)

Impact and Media

Invited media interviews:

Conservatives have a bias for seeing ideal one-night stands as long-term partners, PsyPost (August 2018) Sexually unrestricted women have more distinctive short- and long-term mate preferences, PsyPost (June 2018)

The Science of Sex Podcast (December 2017)

The Psychology of Attractiveness Podcast (May 2017)

The Science of Love, Phil Williams, BBC Radio 5 Live (February 2017)

Media coverage: Russia Today • Sick of How You Smell?, by Dr. Robert Burriss • The Psychology of Attractiveness Podcast • The Psychology of Attractiveness Podcast • This is Money

Conference Activity

Conference and Research Presentations

April 2019, EHBEA, Université Toulouse 1 Capitole

Title: A 54-nation study of ecology, opportunity, and economic inequality.

December 2018, Data Study Group, The Alan Turing Institute

Title: Player pathways: Modelling career paths that deliver success.

September 2018, Seminar Series, The Alan Turning Institute

Title: Listening to the crowd: Data science to understand The British Museum visitors.

June 2018, Seminar Series, The Alan Turing Institute

Title: Using Natural Language Processing to uncover user sentiment on Twitter.

April 2018, EHBEA, University of Pécs

Title: Ecological predictors of female sexual suppression.

April 2017, EHBEA, École Normale Supérieure

Title: He's not my type: Do conservative women only see long-term mates?

August 2016, International Society for Human Ethology, University of Stirling

Title: Sociosexuality predicts women's short- and long-term mate preferences.

August 2016, International Society for Human Ethology, University of Stirling

Title: Disease vulnerability and preferences for self-similar scent.

May 2016, Department of Psychology seminar series, University of Warwick

Title: Perceived vulnerability to disease moderates attraction to immunologically similar scent.

May 2016, Postgraduate Research Day, University of Warwick

Title: Unrestricted sexuality promotes greater distinction in women's short- and long-term mate preferences.

April 2016, EHBEA, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine

Title: Sexually unrestricted women have more distinctive short- and long-term mate preferences.

Industry Presenations

October 2020, Public Health England

Title: Gambling and associated financial, social, and health outcomes in financial transaction big data.

September 2020, Schroders Personal Wealth

Title: The state of the nation: measuring financial health in a representative sample of 6 million individuals.

August 2020, Gambling Commission

Title: Mass-transaction data reveal gambling-related harm.

Teaching

Visiting lecturer University of Birmingham

Natural Sciences book club 2018–2019

MSc Level University of Warwick

Advanced Qualitative and Quantitative Analysis

2016 – 2017

Lectures and workshops designed to teach students statistical analysis using R.

Behavioural Science: Implications and Applications

2015 - 2016

Workshops designed to teach students Agent Based Modelling in MATLAB.

Issues in Psychological Science

2015 - 2017

Workshops and practicals designed to teach core concepts from psychology and decision science.

Methods & Analysis in Behaviour Science

2015 - 2018

Lectures and workshops designed to introduce students to the mathematical modelling of behaviour. Subsequently promoted to session leader, with a role in marking MSc modelling assignments.

Psychological Models of Choice

2015 - 2016

Lectures and workshops designed to teach students decision-making modelling in R and MATLAB.

BSc Level Academic Skills for Psychologists

University of Warwick 2016 – 2018

Seminars with first year undergraduates, helping students develop an academic skill set and a deeper understanding of empirical psychological science.

Human Sexuality 2015 – 2017

Seminars with third year undergraduates, designed to explore theories of human mate choice, using an evolutionary framework.

Research Methods in Psychology

2015 - 2018

Workshops with first year undergraduates, designed to teach core skills, such as experimental design, statistical tests (e.g., *t*-tests, ANOVA), and using SPSS software.

Supervision

Relationship satisfaction and female intrasexual competition (UG dissertation - x2 students) 2016 – 2017

Punishment of promiscuous females in an Ultimatum Game (*UG dissertation - x2 students*) 2016 – 2017

Teaching Qualifications

Teaching and Learning in Higher Education

Completed Oct 2015

A classroom-based qualification based on understanding student approaches to learning, student objectives, and tackling challenging situations. This course required submission of an essay demonstrating reflection on higher education teaching practice and evidence of implementing plans to improve my own teaching practice.

Skills

Programming languages: R, Python, MATLAB, L*TrX, SQL, Markdown and RMarkdown, Shiny, JavaScript, HTML

Software: Teradata, Model Maker, Domino, PsychoPy, NetLogo, SPSS, Qualtrics

Miscellaneous: Professionally trained in Excel modelling and financial modelling

Professional History

Analyst (Graduate Scheme), Financial Modelling, Consulting, Deloitte LLP

Sep 2014 – Sep 2015

Intern, Investment Banking, Credit Suisse

Mar – Apr 2010

Software Architect Operations Partner, Gap Year Internship, IBM

2009 - 2010; Summer 2011

Professional Qualification

Chartered Institute of Management Accountants

Completed Jan 2015

A qualified member of the Chartered Institute of Management Accountants (CIMA) and CIMA certified.